hey folks and welcome to strength weekly
the weekly show that brings you all you
need to know in the strength
[Music]
game I'm David Thomas to joined by my
colleague Phil bman and we have a lot on
the agenda today and just a reminder
strength weekly will be coming to you
every week so tune in for the latest and
greatest for strong folks and hey you
might learn a thing or two to help
yourself get strong in the gym but
before we we get into what's happened
including a new Mr Olympia make sure you
subscribe to barbin on YouTube the very
platform where you're tuning in right
now Phil we have an amazing run of show
should we give the people the rundown on
what we're going to talk about today I
think we should I think we should prep
everybody for what they're about to
encounter a lot of news in the
bodybuilding World here is today's run
of show and new Derek Lunsford wins the
2023 Mr Olympia becoming the 18th man in
history to hold that title and the first
two Division champion in the
competition's history Chris Bumstead the
Canadian Phenom wins his fifth classic
physique title Andrea Shaw Sydney Gillan
and franela Matos they continue their
high stakes epic runs at the top are
they really the most dominating athletes
in the bodybuilding game and segment
four we take a complete U-turn and we
talk about the Bulgarian method for
strength training bust a miss
misconceptions and explain why yeah it's
probably not going to work for you at
home I'll get right ahead of that Phil
of all these big stories today which are
you most excited to talk about I am most
excited about to talk about the dynasty
building within uh each division in the
space right now because I feel like
every single division you could you
could have that sort of debate with the
guys at the top two what I love about
bodybuilding is if you think of who's
the best who's the most dominant
historic placements much like in
basketball there's like a curveball you
can just throw in there it's not Jordan
or LeBron it's Will Chamberlain you know
what I mean bodybuilding has that as
well it's like well you know is it uh is
it Ronnie is it Arnold no it's Phil
Heath you know what I mean like you can
always have this like Dark Horse third
competitor that comes in out of nowhere
and I love that and one thing I'm
excited to talk about today is the most
dominating athletes in today's
bodybuilding scene because it can be
seen about 17 different ways but as far
as dominating athletes we got to talk
about the new champ in the men's open
division Derek Lunsford he not only
becomes only the 18th man to ever hold
the title of Mr Olympia he becomes the
first ever two division winner he won
the men's 22-pound division in 2021 that
was just two years ago is my math
correct there two years ago put on a
ridiculous amount of mass while
maintaining symmetry gets second place
last year behind hadti chopz
the Iranian wolf and then Derrik
lindford comes back this year switches
the order and walks away with the crown
just two years after being the champ at
212 pounds Phil I gotta toss it your way
how unlikely is this progression from
212 champ to men's Open
champ I think if anybody has been
watching Lunsford as he ascended up to
the 212 title back in 2021 and the frame
that that guy had at his I believe he's
5'7 when he first entered the Mr Olympia
contest last year he had mentioned that
he had put on like eight pounds of
muscle tissue now that seems like not a
lot for maybe guys like us who have a
lot of space to grow but for guys that
have already maxed out their physiques
to teeka that kind of additional muscle
tissue in a year's time frame is an
unbelievable amount of mass to pack on
he did bring some good symmetry right I
saw some people on Instagram really
trying to pick apart his physique and
they were really splitting hairs he
didn't have any GL laring gaps in his
physique lower body upper body I mean
the guy brought a very good well-
conditioned package still a
controversial
win do you think and this is just Phil
personally not Phil as a journalist do
you think he should be this year's Mr
Olympia the differences between these
guys is I feel as though they beat each
other in different aspects and I think
shows are won from the back primarily
because there are more points to be
scored from the back now we have to like
we're looking at this stuff through the
a camera lens right and if the the
difference between watching somebody in
a camera lens and seeing somebody up
close in person the muscle density the
striations the graininess of the muscle
that may not translate as well over the
camera as it will in person and I think
that if you were to look at chupan and
really just go off of conditioning he's
Untouchable the man is Untouchable in
that realm I think that's why he won it
last year I think it's why he was in
contention again this year I think the
reason that lford was able to take it
from him this year primarily was because
lunsford's back shots are just
so obviously dominant compared to
everybody else and I think that's what
gave him the couple narrow points Edge
to take the gold if I'm a competitor in
the men's open category I'm a little
scared of wford right now because this
is a competitor who is still in many
ways filling out into the men's open
division he might even have more mass to
pack on and he's the reigning champ now
so transitioning to our Second Story on
the day because we can talk about that
forever bumed continues his Reign he's
the Top Dog in that category five years
in a row um the man really has nothing
left to prove as the top classic
physique competitor in history at this
point because the history of that
division is not so long one thing I want
to ask in tossing it over to you Phil
because I know you have a lot of
thoughts here was this year closer than
last year they don't call Bumstead the
standard for nothing and I think that
Bumstead his physique is exactly the
standard that classic physique is
designed for do you know what I mean he
there's no reason like if he continues
he will never have to like concede the
crown somebody will have to take it from
him and in order to do so they will have
to also be the standard and then come in
with a better standard than him so it's
like guys like Brion he's a brion's a
two-time champ he's comeing fourth the
last two years it's not like Brion has
slipped his conditioning and his posing
are Immaculate that guy is perfection
but like he can't contend with the guys
that are literally the standard of which
they're being they're being judged by he
has also put in the work to make himself
one of the most I'd say tied for tied
for the lead in having the best routines
and moving in a way that best shows off
his physique on stage and that cannot be
understated especially in classic
physique where it is all about
Aesthetics yeah and and it's not like
Bumstead is just being handed the
division because of his popularity I
mean yes the guy has you know 17 some OD
million whatever Instagram followers and
he's like the biggest draw in the
business or whatever it is but like if
you look at look at look at back shots
from when he won his first title to a
back shot now and see the progression
that he has made in that time while
staying at top the mountain I mean the
guy is working it's it is not like he's
he's resting on his Laurels like he's
earning his titles so it's it's not like
anything is being handed to the guy like
he's putting in the effort and it's
paying off make sure if you want to
recap of every ision at the Olympia I
mean we are talking every division make
sure to watch a video that we're going
to link in the description below where
Phil Blackman one of the very faces you
have seen on screen during this
broadcast goes into more detail so I
just want to give that quick shout out
before we get to the next segment which
is on the women's side the shortest rain
we're about to talk about is back to
back to back a three Pat the longest is
a sevene what is that it's not a it's a
a sepa septi sep um and uh Phil we can't
talk about bodybuilding in the Olympia
unless we talk about three big names on
the women side Andrea Shaw Sydney Gillan
and franel Matos Sydney seven wins in a
row seven seven seven seven wins in a
row eight would take her into the realm
of truly legendary alltime great fril
Lam Matos has had the wellness division
in a headlock uh and Andrea Shaw I mean
this is her this is her fourth uh Miss
Olympia in a row
Phil where do these three competitors
rank if you had to throw in seum throw
in Lunsford right uh where do among
those five competitors how might you
rank the current top bodybuilders in the
game I think the guys get a lot of the
clout I think the if you were to look on
a pound-for-pound basis what the women
have done I think the women might be
more impressive and I I say that because
if you look at Andrea Shaw's run of four
consecutive she only has four because
the Miss Olympia came back four years
ago yeah you know it's like it's like it
was gone for like six years and then it
came back and then it's just been
nothing but Shaw the entire time yeah
and also like you you look at what uh
MOS has done in the in the wellness
Division I mean the wellness division is
still new like I can't believe Wellness
is I remember when Wellness was
announced right like wellness was
announced as an Olympia division after
we started covering bodybuilding on Barb
ben.com which was not that long ago like
barbad just didn't cover bodybuilding
for her first like four or five years
right which a lot of people don't
realize like that's still a new division
how long could her Reign
be I don't know is that going to
continue if it does it will be the most
well-earned of any division in the sport
a because it's new so the division is
going to evolve right it's still going
through the Growing Pains of of being a
new Division and it's super close so
okay if you had to rank put Lunsford
seum and those three ladies in the
conversation if you had to go
from let's call it most dominant right
like I like how you bring out Matos has
won every Wellness division that's been
contested at the Olympia but is she the
most dominant that that's actually
probably not the case because we're
seeing that margin of Victory be pretty
narrow because it's a very deep sack
field how would you rank from most
dominant to least dominant right now for
what it's worth I think the most
dominant athlete is the one we talk
about the least because it's always the
expected outcome Sydney Gillan is is the
most dominant of any person in any
division in my mind she's got seven in a
row and it's never been close yeah at no
point has it been close you know I mean
and and and it's not like the other
athletes around her are slouches like
they are the top in the world and it's
and still like it's just like oh yeah
it's Gillan whatever number seven sure
you know go going on number eight sure
like if we think about how many all time
it's like Mr Olympia you got Lee Haney
and Coleman at eight if you look at Miss
Olympia we got Iris Carl at 10 gillan's
at seven and it's not close and she
still got she could compete for another
10 years and it wouldn't be close all
these athletes their entire lives are
built around this bodybuilding like
there's an off season but there's not
really an offseason you this is your
life year around it is focused on this
package you bring to the stage at this
one weekend at this one event right I
cannot stress how much dedication and
discipline that takes but it is so
expected for her to win and has been for
many years that it is rare in the realm
of strength sports for it to be that way
okay so Gillan at the top for most
dominant who would you put at number two
and let's work our way down the list
quickly here I would say uh I would put
Shaw second okay I don't think I I think
Shaw has been just dominant in Miss Miss
Olympia so I I think I would put her
there I think uh Bumstead because he's
the standard for the division like it's
it's very rare that you have somebody
with a physique that they are actually
judging against as opposed to judging
you against a standard like they're
judging you against Bumstead which is
unique in any of the divisions and then
uh under I would put Matos only because
the division is so young if she can get
a fourth and a fifth like I mean we
would have to recalibrate this
conversation but the division is too
young and I think still evolving and so
even though she is one three in a row
her her lead in the division has gotten
narrower and narrower every year to the
point where now it's down to a point so
if the division starts to adjust a
little bit and evolve and she can still
maintain her position at the top then I
would move her up a couple ranks cool
and then and then lford
distant fifth because we don't know bit
of a question mark I think it's going to
change hands every couple of years uh
until either a new exact form is
established or somebody out of the
woodwork just AB actually runs far and
away and is just better on all sides
agree with that Phil thank you we're
gonna change Focus completely and talk
about a a sport that is very
aesthetically pleasing to look at uh but
it is not based on Aesthetics it is
based on weight on the bar Barb's own
Jake Dixon put up what I consider
recently to be the best article actually
explaining what the Bulgarian method is
it's history its implications and what
it means for the sport of weightlifting
today so I do want to give a special
shout out make sure you read the full
article at the link in the description
below Phil when you hear the term
Bulgarian method before reading this
article from Jake what are let's play
some free association what are a few
Concepts that came to mind I think the
only thing that comes to mind for
anybody that doesn't actually know what
methodology is they just think Bulgarian
split Squat and that's it I think that's
I think that's it I think that's that's
the extent that people are like oh
Bulgarian yeah the split squat cool
moving on that's all I think that's all
people would actually know but the funny
part is the Bulgarian split squat has
nothing to do with the Bulgarian style
of training because the Bulgarian style
of training is when you hear that term
it's most closely associated with the
national team coach of Bulgaria for
several decades uh Ivan ABV and he
developed this very intense
high-intensity form of training where
athletes were maxing out their lists
multiple times a day and there were only
actually six lists they were training in
for the sport of weightlifting the
snatch the clean and jerk the back squat
the front squat the power snatch and the
power clean that was it and Stefan Bev
who was one of the most successful
legendary athletes to come out of this
system said in the morning we started
with squats then snatch then clean and
jerk then squats again in the afternoon
we perform snatch clean and jerk and
back or front squats at night we do the
same this is our program every day for 8
to 10 hours we maxed out between 50 and
60 times a day it's unfathomable the
amount of of of work that they that this
methodology incorporates to max out that
many times a day two things a lot of
great athletes did not tolerate this
system well and they fell out of the
Bulgarian weightlifting Federation for
lack of a better term they basically
just couldn't cut it anymore
and ABV plucked them for the
program this
program does not
work for unenhanced
athletes doping regulation testing at
the time was not what it is today and in
fact we have seen the Bulgarian team in
recent decades hit a bit of a wall
because of the amount of doping
violations the Bulgarian system
was a function of a particular time in
the sport with a particular level or
general lack of sophistication for
doping controls it truly was a perfect
storm and it's unlikely we will ever see
the Bulgarian system be a viable
strength training
methodology moving forward in in human
history as long as doping controls are
in place those are my thoughts Phil any
reactions from you no I think you summed
it up pretty well I mean the article
also sums it up really well humans are
only going to progress and get better
over time because the technology around
people and the way that they can train
and the analytics and data that we have
will get better over time but there is
also a a cap at what human capacity is
and I think it's it is reasonable that
if you're like this feels a little
Supernatural it probably is well I would
highly recommend anyone who's interested
in the sport of weightlifting or just
interested in the bounds of human
performance and the science behind human
performance and performance methodology
in any strength discipline to check out
the article from Jake Dixon linked below
that is it for strength weekly it has
been a massive week in strength but
there is plenty more going on this year
and we will be back next week bringing
you the latest and greatest make sure
you subscribe to barbin on YouTube to
stay up to date until then I'm David to
joined by I'm Phil bman thank you
everybody for watching our Olympia
coverage it will only grow and get
better from here and we appreciate you
tuning in cheers
folks
[Music]